If you only have 24 hours in a day,
your success is the pin of the paw,
how you use the 24.
You got to hear me. People talk about open-whip free,
you know, K-turner, warm, buff it.
Listen to me. I don't get how much money you make.
You only get 24 hours in a day.
And the difference between Oprah and the person that's broke
is Oprah uses her 24 hours wisely.
That's it. Listen to me.
That's it. You get 24.
I don't care. You broke. You grew up broke.
I don't care. You grew up rich.
I don't care if you're in college.
You're not in college.
You only get 24 hours.
And I blew up literally.
I went from being a high school drop-out.
To sell in 6,000 books in less than 6 months.
We're after 24 hours.
I was like, okay, Eric, you got to get a grip on you 24 hours
because you bought to be broke for the rest of your life.
And just all I need you to do for me.
I can tell you all about your life.
If you just write down your 24 hour schedule for me,
you let me look at it.
I can tell you where you're going to be.
20 years of you keep that schedule.