meeting open. Welcome everybody. So we'll start with the apologies and I'm
guess we have Hazel. We're only on the same seat here I think. So could I
have a move or please? Andrew just before you did just before you do.
I had to leave the meeting at 130 to attend a future proof meeting. So sorry
about that. So my apologies from then. Good as God. Thanks Jim.
So we should include that and the and the motion as well.
If someone would like to move please. Maybe a move, Mike. Thanks Lou. Thanks Susan.
All in favour. I know. Country know it's carry.
Disclosure of members interests. Do we have any today?
No, well we want to item four late items.
Any late items? No late items. So confirmation of order of meeting. No changes
can. No I don't see any need for for change. We do have a number of
families joining us at the meeting today. But they're well aware of the time. So
I'm yes I'm hoping that will be the required time.
Happy to move Andrew. Graham. Thanks Graham. A second.
A second. Thanks Susan. I think what?
She is all in favour please say aye. I'm not.
I'm not. I'm not really no carried. Okay item six which is confirmation of
the minutes from 18 February. Have we all our take doses being read?
Anything raised from those minutes? Andrew Graham speaking.
My diary showing me that I was at the meeting but my name not recorded there.
Right I was going to bring that up to you. Thank you some.
Mistakes. Thanks Bruce. Okay so I'm sure we can have that remedied Sam.
Yes. Yes we'll make the changes. Thank you. Okay so would that change? Could I have a
mover for the minutes to be received? Is a true and quick rec or please thank you Marcus.
Seconder. I'll second up. Thanks Bruce. All in favour please say aye.
Aye. I. Country no carried. Thank you. Item seven Jason. Has Jason joined us?
The heirs. I see Sam not any high Jason here you're doing.
Good thank you. Great the floor is yours. Okay Sam I don't think we had as we had issues with
trying to get the presentation is that right? Oh no. Sam is sharing brilliant.
Perfect. Thanks Sam. Good morning or good afternoon sorry everyone. Thanks for allowing me
time just to give you a quick update on where we are as a sector for tourism and particularly for
wipe-hard district. So our report has obviously been provided to you and prepared which was our
last six months performance at the end of 31st December 2019 as you would have seen wipe-hard
district council was going through significant growth. Probably one of the fastest growing
regions for us with regards to tourism impact. You were experiencing double digit growth pretty much
through visitor expenditure and also commercial accommodation. But we are here today to
discuss this obviously a bit of a change in the dynamic given COVID and the impact for tourism
particularly as a sector. Go to the next slide Sam. Perfect. So just first a couple of slides
obviously just covering off some data we're now receiving international data on a weekly basis
from the government and also from the airlines. So I've no surprise obviously since COVID locked down
an international trip or restrictions we've put in place. International visitor rivals in
gym New Zealand has been having been dropping it at a very sharp rate. We still do have E-line
connectivity which I will go through because we are still maintaining what we call a baseline
service for connections across the world mainly for repatriation flights but also for cargo and
service across the country as well. Next slide Sam. So weekly hand transitions again no surprise
obviously overall our visitor expenditure is down significantly but when you do look on to the
left top five obviously food like our infamuses we are still seeing some cumulative in some obviously
weekly growth and expenditure compared to all our other visitor type experiences and
changes as well. Thanks Sam. So the impact for us is a sector again look I mean
maybe all of this has been reported but just to cover off in summary we were already impacted
through the loss of China group travel which started in the second to last week of January.
So with that all of our international facing products our hotels, our motels, our E-BNBs
were immediately impacted by that because many of China group travel actually did stay in the
white puddle they were our fourth largest international visitor market behind Australia North America
in New Can Europe. It did shut us down pretty much once international travel restrictions had us
and the visitor economy covers more than just the tourism operators again with mentioned accommodation
it also impacts retail hospitality transport providers our operators of course but also
event organizers in major venues and of course mystery creek of anti-drym in Lake Hada pedal
a key of the in platforms for white puddle district. We have had significant job losses in
business closures across tourism. I have done underneath that last bullet point look the
immediate business impact that we have been coaching our businesses through and helping them get
through. There's some have gone to what we call temporary or seasonal closure so again we have a lot
of seasonality and tourism many who would close for winter have closed but those are potentially
of never closed before we have suggested they go into hibernation and so that's what we're calling
temporary seasonal closures we've had a number of businesses you know Hobarton was obviously
one of the most public ones reported in the media but again all our motels hotels retail hospitality
have pretty much reduced service and staff is only essential services operating as we know
but again with alert level three we do see some opening up potentially in the hospitality sector
for white power anyway and then the last obviously implication for us is we have had a number of
businesses who are permanently closing not only of these are lost definitely to the tourism
industry to try and bring people back when we don't have products but also particularly for
those vulnerable communities where some of these operators have been going for many years thanks
to seeing. Can I ask a question about that? Sure have you got examples of what businesses
they're struggling and like what who isn't closing by who is closing and how it isn't
pecking around the one district? Yeah so particularly for white power it has mainly been
your hospitality potentially some of your retail and also accommodation so we have had many
nearly all of your accommodation has pretty much gone into hibernation or closure
they're calling it temporary closure but there's some of them have been able to access the
white subsidy which is great but again what we're going to see is the impacts along the in the
12 week wage subsidy right now so it's post 12 weeks what we're quite concerned about
we have been lobbying nationally the government and I think that's all sectors not just tourism
around potentially extending the white subsidy for 20 weeks because it will take a lot to restart
the tourism sector again people it's propensity to travel is quite low we will travel locally
and potentially we will travel intra-regionates to stay within the region but
to try and stand up the domestic travel market is going to be a long haul they were looking
at it six to 12 months recovery plan for that. Great so lastly look at I mean
and nothing else that's probably here this was just something we do for industries people
know where we are fit so from the tourism perspective when we respond obviously we're providing
industry support right now at a national level regional level and also a local level but then
we have to walk our chambers of commerce our business associations and all our government
have been great and actually supporting us with what we call the business and community
sort support site for tourism businesses and then lastly we're obviously partnered with
the Civil Defence Network work around providing welfare support not just for tourism operators
again it's also being utilizing tourism operators many of our caterers have now been
repurposed into providing food services pretty much all supporting the food banks and
actually cooking meals we also have a number of our transport operators and tourism being
run basically requisitions now to provide transport options and actually getting people around
such as essential workers in many of the staff potentially we've been redeploying
into the Civil Defence Network through providing security and welfare and
call centre as well so not only are we also working with Civil Defence also putting staff into
the as well. Even though we're obviously dealing with Covid this is just for you to be
aware there are obviously continuing issues that we're going on with Covid and with the tourism industry
first up was domestic airline connectivity so again New Zealand has been pretty open that they
will not be restarting until a little level one so we meet with in New Zealand weekly just to see
how we will try and stand the industry back up again they're going to focus very much on what
we call an incremental restart so it's doing all the work in brief strategy across the country
so potentially maybe only two or three flights into Hamilton per day but again it's the try and get
their reach across the whole network first before they can actually stand up and have a full
schedule like we have seen at a Hamilton Eagle particular over the last three before years.
airline connectivity internationally is still continuing so those are just some summary of some
of the ones that are still flying so again New Zealand are still connecting into North America and Hong Kong
into Australia, Fiji Airlines are still flying into Fiji on a daily service and Qatar has
probably probably used the most to try and repatriate northern hemisphere travellers back to their
homes through Qatar and then also Korean airlines are still operating a daily service as well.
For future again in New Zealand are saying they will be focusing very much on the domestic market
first they will traditionally be a domestic airline for the first six to 12 months and domestic
also includes Australia in the Pacific. American Airlines so far have been the only one we've met
with who planned to return to New Zealand from October 2020 so they have put a stake in the ground
to say when they will start flying into New Zealand again. Now the reason why I just raised
international airline connectivity is because it will take this country at least two to five years
before we ever go back to the type of connectivity we've had as a country previously before lockdown.
So again it's going to be a very long boom for us as a country to regain international
visitor rivals with senior the past. Air Trevor control services up for review the reason why I
just put that in there is just to let everyone know there was no whi-cutter wear ports or earfields
but particularly Hamilton Epoot as an impacted but for us in the central North Island, Routalua is
one that is going to be impacted around potentially the closure of air traffic control to our
services that will mean potentially that we will be re-deverting the domestic network through
Toronto and Hamilton so unfortunately for Routalua's last it could be our game and then lastly we've
still got the investigation underway around Fakari White Island so the work safe investigation
should be going to a close shortly there will be impacts on the tourism and suppliers around
adventure tourism for this country and also we will be at waiting qualmark which is our
accreditation program particularly around health and safety for the country.
Thanks Sam.
Just some of the things that dates are some new we are now. Field days is going online so from the
30th of June for two weeks. Field days will be providing a virtual exhibition space
very similar to other international events you offer this type of experience. Again it does
a trial but we do hope to bring Field days back in 2021 obviously not only is the largest major
event for WIPAR but it's definitely for the WIPAR to be a good economic impact. We worked
due to hosting the Zealand tourism awards in November that has been postponed until next year
so we will reset the date for that. Explore and trends these are what we call our two main
international trade shows. The obviously being delayed trends 2021 which is the main time when we
actually sell the WIPAR to the world we will not be having until maybe June next year so it's
just the waiting on a date for that. Two major convention centres were due to open the
year to pay and Christo which potentially is the one that will be taking a lot of business away
for us for business events that is now being delayed for another year and of course that in
New Zealand International Convention Centre we will not know the reopening date of that until
they work through the final insurance claims. So again by having these two convention centres
not operating means that places like Trudlands and the Mystery Creek of Bint Centre are going to be
filling the gap for national and international conferences for the short term which is actually
a good opportunity for us again as a region post-COVID. But we also do still have a Vint plane
so the major events obviously the National Waka Amos at this stage still plans to take a
take a take a fit and let cut up here though and we also have our first major event for the region
that ICC woman's cricket wheelcarts scheduled for the 8th of February again. This one will
particularly be decided by around October no Vimba whether we are international travel restrictions
have lifted to enable some of the players to come otherwise they will have to go into if it
does continue until isolation until the cricket wheel cup can be held. So what we have seen
particularly for other parts of the sector is that Vint has been more postpone for
Wipa and for the wider Waka to region rather than completely cancelled or not returning. So
there is some positivity for us as we do see this is the lead sector to enter a covering
economically and socially for the district. Excite Sam.
Response we have a what we have three tier response plan obviously this is no similar to everyone
else right now we have a mitigate process with security and now we then have a restart phase and
then we have a reimagined phase. So initially in the response phase no different to everyone.
Now lots of briefings a lot of support we obviously have been faced to face briefings across all the
sector long before the shutdown and now we move to the virtual space we are still doing
ever-concerning national level to try and make sure we can access more business support for the region.
Some of the gap right now at a government support and out of the support that Waka can provide
does it doesn't cover any employees for 100 employees plus. So that's quite this quite the point
end of town we call it for most of our region for our big employers. Again weight subsidy okay
but on the outside of that there's actually no large industry support so we've been pushing
that through government to try and unlock some of that if this lockdown continues we've been doing
one or one operated chickens we have 240 listed operators for us so again these are daily
to weekly chickens by all our teams to make sure we've been able to access business advice
and some of the wage support we've been doing webinars and we've now moved in the last two weeks
into workforce read deployment so again we've been taking some organisations on employers that
have maybe at least five to ten staff members displaced through to Hobbiton who had one of the
largest that around 270 and actually redeploying them and offering them redeployment options
into the Kiwi Freedom Distry we've placed a 110 staff into Kiwi fruit with transport from Hobbiton
as well as the avocado industry which will be the next seasonal workforce will be
will be standing up until the end of the year but put staff into supermarket civil defense
security and also there've been providing some services from home but again what we are going to
see over the next two weeks and we're starting to measure that is the full unpaid so people
that we cannot read the point that potentially will be able to work so our theory is currently
a survey underway and we'll be updating all councils in the government around the overall
impact for tourism and why cuts in.
Under the restart phase so again we want to congratulate local government because obviously
getting some of those shovel-rooted projects through with the Crown Infrastructure Partners
for their consideration is a great win for the region but potentially for the sector pretty much
every district has put up around one to tourism and projects as part of shovel-rooted so again
we do need to focus on the future and how we'll restart the region research and we were
already in market and about to finish up our domestic perceptions and majorly research
this is now becoming quite timely for us and will help us inform around how we will try and
bring back the domestic travelers into the region based on some of the research we've undertaken.
We're also working on a major in business events restart campaign so that planning has been
underway for a couple of weeks so that when we're ready to go we can push go on that we do see
events and business events and corporate travel is being the kickstarter we need for economic
and social recovery across the region new developments again you've all got new developments going on
potentially in your regions head and leg obviously one of your newest hotels in Cambridge
and open dog Christmas Eve so Glinder and the team will be keeping in touch with quite a lot
because they haven't been in operation very long they're impacts are quite severe so again
making sure that we still have some future developments that will continue across the region
to take us through the next stage data and insights I've touched on them now gone to
weekly so again we're sharing that information in to Walker and now we've been shooting
into the to Walker economic outlook as well which is great and then lastly the mighty local
campaign was launched two weeks ago and it's definitely around the restart phase thanks.
So mighty local again was a partnership with ourselves to Walker all the chambers of
commerce so to our mood to obviously Cambridge Chamber of Commerce plus the Wacatto Chamber of
Commerce all our councils the business associations it all exists in some communities and
all our regional eye sites we're in phase one so for the last two weeks we've been promoting
businesses with contactless delivery promoting you know on people that are still doing
entertainment online or virtually from within Wacatto recipes from our beloved chefs well-being
and fitness and this week we launched business stories so again we're starting to use this
platform to promote some of the businesses and how they're pivoting into obviously response
or looking at different opportunities for the business so the idea is to try and give people hope
during phase one during phase two which is obviously from a loot level three we will increase
the article and eat from bee listings and also essential services are starting to grow as well
and phase two we will move more to a local phase at the moment it's a regional platform
but the idea is potentially people we're able to to to have to group the types of
information in services available at a local delivery level and at a district level as well
and then phase three which has been hopefully all travel restrictions are lifted
we will then activate the basically the the bi-local eat local event local shop visit and explore
within the region and obviously that's in partnership with many communities and business
associations that already have local programs such as Cambridge with the totally locally Cambridge
campaign so we're working with Kelly and the team around how we're trying
push the program rather than this one once we give to phase three
thanks him
and when it comes to how we will actually respond long term so at the moment we're in phase one
so we're calling it the hyper local phase so one to three months we'll be pushing basically localism
everything to do with obviously how you purchase an inter-equal via local community
it phase two which will move into a three to six month break at we're estimating we can then
start to do inter-regional travel so we're targeting the drive market within the wide-cut or region
we hopefully starting to stand up community events again they can have a local level
and regional business meetings might be able to begin again with social distancing
at level three which is what we're planning our scenarios for six to 12 months we can then
stand up the domestic market that is when potentially we will mainly focus on drive so
as you've heard me say before 2.5 potentially 3 million people live within three hours radius
of the wide-cut region including the region itself so we'll definitely be focusing on the drive
market national events will be returning as well as national meetings and then eventually corporate
travel which again business are quite a good lead for us with regards to our stand-up
for the sector again and then lastly we're planning on one to two years before we
actually start to see any sort of international impact again. Short haul markets into Australia
and the Pacific will open first and then we will eventually move back into major events
international conferences and starting to bring back the corporate and leisure travel market into
wide-cut also that's the time frame we are currently doing our scenario planning for but as we
may change every week based on your levels we have.
And then lastly Rea Meijan so you would have seen that last week or actually two weeks ago as
well the government announced that there was a call to reshape and re-imagined the tourism industry
so we have been pushing for the last two to three months with tourism, New Zealand and the
Minister for Tourism around what we're calling a re-imagining of tourism where we there was our
chance that this is more than a shock it's actually a bit of a circuit breaker for the sector and for
all business sectors for us all to look and see how could we do our businesses differently.
We all knew that tourism was growing in quite an exponential rate and there were some areas
that were really filling the pressure such as Queen's Town in central Otago and Cathedral Cove
some of our sites Mount Tomaruto so for us now it's great to see the government are taking
the seriously so we're now working with tourism, New Zealand to lead our new plan,
to be particularly internationally but also look at all these types of questions you know we're
our previous visitor rivals and expenditure growth right for the region what will success
it look like for us for the future for a visit a market how we move our sector from boom and
bus to gain no different to the food and fiber sector or any other person's cycle and lastly
how do we move to more sustainable community tourism and for us and the Whicat's of what we call
creating net benefit rather than just benefiting those their potentially we're making money out of tourism
we want to see community thrive and that they have the decision around what sort of tourism they want
so again we will be moving our 2016 tourism opportunities plan which many of you were involved in
we will now be developing a destination management plan and that will be happening nationally as
to try and what we call transform tourism for the beta so there is no such word as recovery now
we will not be receiving the same sorts of level of tourism as we did previously but neither we might
not have the same sort of services and opportunities available in tourism as well post COVID so
again it is a good opportunity for us to have a transform in the sector.
I think we've got one more. Looking lastly to obviously I call it to all my life government partners
I really appreciate everyone helping to promote your rates for the emissions and installment policies
not just for the tourism sector but for all business. It's great to see you all continuing with
your resource consent process maybe in a more delayed way but again the liquor and food
license is going to be more important for us particularly we try and stand up after a little three
we still have the regional major event strategy activations so again we are still awaiting some
a decision from well energy trust about potentially helping to establish a regional major
of in-spun which will actually assist all the districts to be able to bid for major events again
and also to attract and bid new major events into our shallvases and across the region and then
lastly again just to thank you all for your continual funding to support the tourism industry and
that would obviously be more important through restart in the re-imagined phase and again the
point I made earlier we will not be recovering to pre COVID levels for at least two five years
as a sector and as a region. That's pretty much it from me. Thank you. So happy to take any questions.
Thanks Jason. I got to say that's a fantastic response to what must have been a
massive shock to the industry. And of course in white power and probably a lot of white
care to as well. The mystic tourism is actually a lot bigger than international so we really want
to see and as you have in your plan that being worked on as soon as it's become a possibility.
But yeah does anyone have questions just put your hands up or can see you all clear?
Okay yes that thanks a lot Jason and you are fantastic. If I think being put in by all your team
in the situation a couple of questions well the first one was that I noticed that in the
original major of being strategy these are new funding partner mentioned is that the well-energy
relationship was it? Great you said it's well-energy. Yeah and that's great. And the other thing
is for your reimagining the future of tourism I saw that you had your stakeholders listed.
I didn't see the Department of Conservation there not that they are a tourism operator but most
of our popular destinations I think of Cathedral Coves they are actually managed by the Department
and I just wonder if it would be worthwhile trying to get them around the table because I hear
they worry about the pressure points that we were experiencing and that just having their input
might be beneficial. Yeah it's not so absolutely so you're sorry about that clear.
Department of Conservation are part of that so it's actually a joint tourism, New Zealand and Dock
review of tourism and it's only because they both actually contributed to the national tourism
of tier-all strategies so they're definitely part of it we don't obviously have a lot of
any national parts but we do still have a lot of crown estate in some of the crown estate in our region
or obviously so about our waterfalls and lake areas so again and along our rivers we just
and they will be engaging in that as well because we did obviously have some opportunities with Dock
originally before COVID so the developing short walks for the region and the right walks
mental so there's some projects that we now have bought forward again to say can we'll
dock reconsider moving some of those solidly still. Yeah that sounds fantastic you know welcome.
We have any other questions. Liz yeah I guess just a huge thank you Jason to the support you
have operators you know I've been affected a little myself and the calls that I get from your
Tina appearing encouraging it's very certain. Just one of the things I just wanted to
check in with you on and that's we do have a presentation a little bit later for the moment
the territory and I see you've also given me some support and that's really great who are
aligned on a lot of the international visitors and I guess it's lucky for us in some ways that
there's not that many white power operators that are aligned on international's.
I'm going to tell you as probably one of them perhaps our eyesight to a certain degree in
civil-scient national kiss but other than that do you think that there are any other
aspects of white power that are going to be greatly affected with international's because it's
really with the biggest you know issues going to be. It's mainly going to be the sports
sports code so I think if we can try and get some of the international sporting events back up
running as soon as possible depending on travel restrictions they would be the main and
peak for white power but you are correct look pretty much most of our events which are great
and our operators pretty much talked to the domestic market and I still feel that again look
the white country of expressway and probably other work that potentially has been put forward
for Shabba Riddie even extending expressway down to Pied Edy that that's just all going to help
that ease of domestic travel and we do see the push from self drive obviously the motor home
in Caravian association they are going to be another first lead up and move it back into the region
as well which is fantastic so we're going to be a demon AA traveler around trying to get more
people back into white power so I think again your geographic location, your natural environment
and also your have been played for some hold you on a stronger position around obviously
recovery of your other parts of our region. Great okay thanks very much for that you
you've done an awful lot of work and you've got a lot more in front of you I can see
but that's great and if we've got no more queries I'll we have a recommendation do we have a move
a please thanks Marcus thanks Claire on favour please say aye I
country no carried thanks very much Jason all the best thank you I rely on you thank you
and thank Sam good work yes I see we have Matt sorry Matt Morgan with us yet and also
Kelvin and Andrew are at the air we'll get to you guys before long but Matt from CEE
Hamilton Airport yeah the floor of what yours and no I just like Jason I'm you have had a mess of
change of your business so yeah the tea here you're going on. Thank you thank Andrew and thanks
for the opportunity uh welcome to all of the uh elective members um hopefully we've got a presentation
coming up and that should be before you now uh look today I've also got Scott Kendall my finance manager
thank you so Scott will deal with a couple of the finance slides and uh as most of what we
have to talk you about is and and the rooms are finance so I'm just for the heaven here
perhaps not quite the presentation I had intended to present a month ago but as we know a lot has
changed and a mess of a mount has changed for rail in the in the last three or four weeks so the
presentation is is primarily in a frequency and move to the next slide as primarily around the
COVID-19 response for rail but I thought and there's about eight or nine slides to the key
slides to take you through and I think what you'll see is how we've dealt with the crisis
what the implications have been for the group now and for the next 15 months and uh and a summary
that um shed some some positive light at the end of the tunnel um thanks Sam if we move on um
so I guess the first point I think is useful too um you've obviously received our six-month
interim results some say you're only as good as your last results but sadly that's not the uh
not quite the case today but look we were traveling extremely well very very good first uh six
months and in fact on target for a record of financial performance uh under any measure um of our
SII for this this financial year but of course and that lead to our draft yes or why that you've also
received and uh that of course is now pretty much irrelevant and I see that you are ironically
having a pinned at sleta to my chair Barry Harris about um about OSI and as you can imagine we are
working very uh quickly towards a revised S.W.I for the next three years um
particularly the financials but also there'll be some narrative change and some priority changing as well
we have us to say um completed a very detailed 15 month forecast through the 30 June next year
that will form of course now part of the year one of the um of the S.W.I so look we have a um we have a
presentation the row board and myself has a presentation to all share holding councils in May
and we by that stage we'll have finalized the new drafts um so um moving
all right moving on to the next slide um so I think now just looking at the um the impact and look
very difficult to um well it's very easy to explain in simple terms it's had a massive impact
on the business but if I divided into these four areas that are before you of course the first
result is the aeronautical business um in New Zealand complete as you know suspension of flights
so uh for us that was an immediate um loss of income really from April but from the last week of March
and along with our general aviation L3 Harris Supply at school basically you know 97 98
descent loss of our aeronautical income overnight um terminal flows and we really operating
as an emergency medical um service only at the airport um had the same impact on our
on our property but in fact our property is our lifeline that I will come to but again really overnight
impact on our tendencies we're quite a large landlord as you know and um but to date and
Scott will talk a wee bit about this but today we've had good support from our tenants um but we're
early days as we know into the next sort of three to six months as businesses work through how they're
going to operate uh and survive during this process um we've obviously suspended the terminal um
upgrade work and I'll talk to that a bit further on which of course was a major piece of work
approximately 15 million dollars of of proposed work. A hotel has been sorry if we can just go back
to the previous slide Sam the hotel um impacted significantly as well uh fortunately during April we
was um uh taken over by Ministry of Health as a isolation facility it wasn't required it was a
backup to the Auckland hotels um nonetheless we have received um and we are receiving payment for
the use of the hotel by the government but that ends really this week and from then on um a
difficult times ahead and we'll talk about that and um obviously our people um all my team are working
remotely that's working very very well um might sort of a live in a 12-hour immediate COVID team response
but of course the cafe and store staff um our at home unable to work and part of the government
subsidy our rescue far teen does remain on site at this point so that's really been the impact
what have we really tried to do about if we could move to the next slide um first of all we we are
very quickly leading into um probably uh two weeks before we moved into uh level two and level three
before we even knew what that meant uh we had worked very closely with the board around a pandemic plan
how we would operate the business and more importantly started to look at some scenario and modeling
at that point um that and there's Jason would have mentioned earlier on as borders such as China
we're we're closing to tourism we also saw the writing on the ward on the wall for our
aim business so that plan was developed and approved by the board before we even went into lockdown
we've completed significant cost reductions in the business that's right across the business
of its major cost reductions in our fence lines, reductions pretty much across our business
in terms of payroll, anything up to a 20% reduction and the board have also taken a reduction
and their direct defeats um we applied for and received the government wage subsidy across the group
and uh with the hotel we worked through and I still working through with jet park
but they've gone through a full restructuring exercise number of people have been made redundant
and number have been retained under the government subsidy but we have a meeting later this week with
jet park to look at stage two earpour association that we're part of us doing a major piece of work
uh with central government to try and see what our support of any there are for earpour companies
that have been significantly hurt as you know we are we're long-term infrastructure owners
or quite significant capital to maintain the assets um so there's a piece of work going
on in that space really cover the people we can move to the next slide
the scenario modelling that I talk about there um I think the point
that I'll that I'll make here and come back to at the end is that um
most earpour companies particularly regionally airport companies are significantly
hurt and hit now um we are fortunate that um that we've made the decision
our five or six years ago that the board then under under the leadership of John Spencer and
then implemented by myself and my team uh we've we have as you know dive out of the airport
company and that is I guess bought us time so we have completed um a very conservative
model for igen's sake that it assumes no in New Zealand activity of any uh of any meaningful
sense before October this year uh no and then only a recovery of about 40% of passenger numbers
through uh 2021 calendar year um and well into 2022 before we have a positive eve at dar really
so what is and we've also taken a very conservative view of our our
leases of our leases ability to pay us etc no activity out of the hotel really for the balance
of this under year uh so very very uh conservative but realistic modelling
fortunately we have a major land so that is unconditional and uh very extremely good
family uh significant family multinational business that have agreed to further provide
a letter of credit to the airport company which gives me confidence to to build the road so to speak
so um that delivers about two and a half million dollars of of margin of free cash flow
into the group early next year so the reality is that we can get through this year and through the
June 21 almost a slightly positive cash position the balance sheets taken a bit of a hurt and
Scott will take you through that but um and also we have some work going on on central precinct and
again we have the ability hopefully to settle some unconditional land sales with the same degree
of confidence around further charities which will also feed some additional cash into the group
um we've only utilized about 65% of our depth funding and in fact we have further facilities
that we were intending to take anyway pre-covert and we will still take which will take our funding
up to about 30 million and then we will have only utilized not much more than 50% of that by June
next year so most most of the cash burden is is funded out of um at about overdraft during this period
and then the land sales kickback and we're back in positive space, be in safe very supportive
and no no issues there around funding. Next slide please.
So we have joined with Hamilton City and and I have spoken to Gary Diet and others around the
obviously the Crown Infrastructure Projects we have put forward two applications if you've had a
chance to review um the submission machine might would be aware there are 23 projects we have
submitted for the Terminal Redevelopment and also for an amalgam of a number of projects around
the airport that deal with roading lateral infrastructure, our wastewater plant and um various other
aspect that the gain is also worth about 11 million dollars so we have um put those in
with the West successful who knows but under the Terminal Redevelopment project we're ready to go
tenders have been received and and being evaluated the week of lockdown um our consenters in
with what we're in with your council at the moment and that's um well there was well underway so
it is a shovel really project um we could be able to ground um and doing enabling works within a month
of uh a funding line the key for myself and the board will be what are the tags that the government
apply if we are successful to the funding mechanism how much of it is um is the loan is a grant,
etc that's underway and that's part of our recovery program so if we go to the next slide
been important as we've worked through really the devastation of the power through four weeks to
make sure that we still keep our eye on the longer term um for the group and our focus over the next
12 months I won't spend any detailed time here other than to let you know that we have a
a clear set of a clear business plan and a clear set of objectives for FY 2021 um most of
those remain in place we are reviewing them currently as a management team but we are trying to make
sure that um we continue uh property is a major contributor as you can see the effort to
shy bake million dollars in land sales in the next 12 month period um operations we continue to
maintain um the runway fortunately in our 10 year asset management plan we have a very
quite we just spent close to a million dollars uh finishing in March of this year on some
apron works and some pumps uh some other bits and pieces uh but we have a very quite
capital expenditure for era in order to call over the next 12 to 18 months which couldn't have
come at a better time but we maintain the assets and you need to know that we that we uh that we will
um when it comes to we'll be working very closely with Ian Zeland to try and obviously kickstart
services again and so our whole marketing and our social media and con strategy will be around exactly
that. I hope tell us a much more difficult um uh beast is you would have gained from uh Jason's
presentation but look um we uh we are working now closely with Jet Park to understand what a uh
what a plane coming out the other side may look like fortunately it's a hotel uh that wasn't
reliant on international tourism but it is reliant on uh conferencing uh in particular and uh we
we yet to understand the behaviour of the business community as we go forward in this new world so
we have just almost a foot spinning most of four million on the hotel just prior to lockdown um
so uh it is a it's a it's a it's a property that um we're going to have to um maintain in the meantime
in fund and our conservative modelling does um does mean that the group can um fund its interests
in the hotel uh send me for the next 18 months with um limited activity from it and if we move
down to the next slide which is probably uh the financial certain couple of slides here on
on sort of financials and and all it's got to lead and now my our overarching comment here would
be you had a lot of detail in the six month uh interim results so we decided there was no point
in replicating information you will have read so Scott will summarize it here and more importantly
take you out the other side over the couple of years. All right good afternoon everyone and
thanks Matt for the introduction um yeah I went to I'll too much on the past because it's um
unfortunately to become largely irrelevant but I guess just some key takeaways to the slide and
and what you may have read already um an interim report but it's really that my maintain we've
built in the past couple of years around a um sustainable so recurring revenue base through
passenger growth and the year partners through a property portfolio that it continued really well
for the first half of the year um and go obviously without covered in 19 we expected to continue
to the full year and beyond um yeah just some points around property obviously talking um some
big numbers for our land sales I guess that they are land sales that have been contemplated um
under a 10 year plan the land sales and the pipeline it's not something that we've done
as a new direct reaction um also of a five-cell type arrangement just to get some cash from
next couple years these are um the land we're selling is um sort of surplus to your an Oracle
in fact matcha but it's actually physically separated from the airport through a gallery system so
we're not compromising any core assets sort of um future accountability by selling this land
very much as um land it's surplus the airport so it's why it's being sold off um time it has been
um yes just with the hotel obviously it is a new investment for us the new industry and best
sitting um really pleased with the early trading performance um yeah and probably placing that we didn't
others in the initial money to do the property up um the 10-distant deferred maintenance and things
it's actually traded cash flow positive has no to be profitable with the appreciation things but um
fact ranch able to repay some debt and you know the it's the early vital signs of an occupancy
and rem rate have been I've been certainly in lime expectation and again kind of right up until
February March it was really just coming to a stride round the conference center and the food
beverage offerings so yeah um I think you know it was um you know it was looking really positive
um and hopefully you don't yet the other side that's the O-Momington weekend um we can
leverage off the end so I'll just look um look to the future now just to most of the next slide
um please yeah so given here just sort of um and six-month-themed increments um the remainder of the
financial year um also the financial year that we're in and then the following is for a little
presented and the draft statement and the 10-distant received I think I'm important to focus on
the debate because that's sort of a cash flow metric for us um that includes land sales but it
excludes the courses cost like depreciation which um is around three million dollars a year for us
which in the short term um it's not necessarily linear with the within investment we make into
assets so seeing um obviously seeing a reasonably significant decline in the in the next um and
this calendar year with um across the bus and certainly going to suffer and that's um as we see
and that's sort of early six months between the summer 20 and June next year that's
if we've picked a large land sale um taking a fit and then as the bus is kind of gets back on
its feet um you can see it's slowly back to cash flow positive so I guess you want to compare the
read the read and the blue the blue bars and read land and the green light is sort of the within
we're going to head now so you can see it differently the next sort of 15 to 18 months it's
going to be a bit painful um but after that um too much back on our feet and not becoming
heavily reliant on unland sales sitting out past an exciting month so we've only seen what's already
under contract in what's under conditional seatbelt in those numbers so I think that's um the
conservative but realistic and conservative on both fronts um sitting at a cost where looking
to remove out of the bus and there's only anything that's going to compromise a long term
we're not giving out capability but um either we've built a with managed to hang on too
for as long as we have I think there's some um yeah a different conservative and look at things
don't play up the way we see them doing and certainly not as positive as um and what I do
there's some opportunities if um further but for now it's um this sort of as real estate that we can
preserve a current capability anywhere um yeah I guess just overlay the neat profit slide
yeah there's a lot more um probably that the deficits are bigger largely because of the
affected appreciation but ultimately following a fairly similar trend of the cash flow that um
look land sales over the next 18 months will give us um cash flow positive and we expect by
the in the bus and to be largely cash flow positive from its recurring trading to be sustainable
and yeah that's probably I guess um the main takeaway there and it's not really built into the
slides but just um it's marked all about the fit on the balance sheet look we expect that there
will be some impacts so a balance sheet around property values and those sort of equally
movements um so as a shareholder that obviously will impact your accounts as well but um I guess
out of this is as a as a shareholder and a non financial sense um um animal list we're preserving
our core capability um we're not compromising any of our numerical capability um I think yeah in terms
of what the service will keep delivering um that shouldn't be compromised or at least our
ability to do it um that was really well our head just um they have a view of the financials
so it might be perfect to map to wrap up. This is their last slide um my apologies it's
it's certainly taken a bit of your time but look I think the key themes here really are as I opened
we we we we um hit this situation in a very strong position um and uh in a very strong balance sheet
a record year um the foresight of the diversification through our 10-year group strategy um
here's I think really bought this company time uh perhaps unlike some other regionally
reports that I think we'll need to go to the shareholders very uh quickly for additional funding
or through the of through their bank funding lines um we don't need to um that non-revenue has been
absolutely critical to to and in fact ironically we never predict of a COVID-19 scenario but we
did predict um a loss of erinordical income uh through um cessation of services or reduced services so
has been one of the same uh and look um overall um the recovery's Scott has mentioned will be modest
but sustainable um and as I want to keep restating uh we won't need to go to our core debt at this stage
or funding lines to to to fund us we can fund it um uh out of uh in effect the working capital
um and most importantly I think for you as the shareholder's there is no requirement for the board
to come to a shareholders for support and we don't see a scenario at all that um that requires
a shareholder's to assist the poor company um in the foreseeable future so that's it from me
sorry Andrew I apologize that we're over time but um have you to take questions if you've got time?
Yeah no thanks guys um I think we were aware that um a bit of extra time was going to be required
for you guys with uh such a mess of impact um I just got a quick question about the flight school um
would they not get back to level one or possibly could they operate a level two?
Uh well in fact Scott's just had some advice today it could well be that the pilots that are
are well through their qualification will be able to start flying under level three so as soon as
next week we could see some flight activity um but it will be to your point Andrew down at level one
probably but there'll be the social distancing issues when you have an instructor
and a trainee pilot on board so I think we're still around clear and so are L3 as to when that will be
um I think it's worth noting that um we don't quite know where we're going to go over the L3
in the sense that they've got a hundred about a hundred and eighty pilots currently um at the
Hamilton or out at the accommodation at um at the airport so I think we were far out there
fine for the next few months the question is how whether they're going to be the logistics of
moving pilots across borders for training and actually pilots uh there is not a death of pilots
in the global marketplace as a result of the catastrophe catastrophe for the airlines so I think those
two would suggest to us that um we've got difficult times ahead past the end of 2020 with L3
yeah they make sense um yeah I think um it's as you've both noted um the stage that you
you're at with your um property development has has been a very fortunate thing of if this had
occurred at the at the beginning of that it would have been far more um financially destructive
but does anybody else have any queries? Okay that not been case look thank you very much I
have a really comprehensive update and um great to see um you recovered from the shock and um
being really positive and and uh constructive going forward so thanks very much to you both
thanks thank you everyone thank you thank you I think it is and I see we have killed and
I suppose sorry what was that? Ah okay so we got Kelvin and also as Peter available
yes I am oh great so thanks Kelvin and Peter and we'll fit you get onto the
um sheet services. Thanks Mr Chairman and thanks for the opportunity to speak with you the
South and the Nurn you've been provided with a copy of the company statement of intent and
half yearly report to 31 December 2019 and I I'm conscious of the fact this is the first opportunity
they have had is the newest chair of the last two talk to you so I wanted to start by just briefly
introducing myself and then I wanted to talk a little bit about the company's transformation role
how are we going to do things differently what it means for your council and then I want to
conclude with some remarks about Covid-19 but I guess the key point is that certainly from the
board of last perspective the organisation has never been more relevant than it will be in a post
Covid-19 recovery period so the first point I wanted to make is that my family has been heavily
invested in the White Cutter for a very long time my mother's family came to this region in 1865
my father's family came to this region in 1880s and all my family live in the region my mum
lives in Hureki district my sister lives in Thames Coromandle I have another sister in Hamilton
a brother in White Park district and after 44 years and she and I are leaving Auckland next week
and moving to Cambridge so we very much look forward to becoming a White Park district council
rate payers as from the 1st of May so as you can see my family's been heavily invested in the
success of the region and it's one of the reasons I took the job that the other reason is the
clarity of the opportunity and I've spent 21 years in local government governance across multiple
CCOs and clarity of role is actually quite unusual in this case the company's version is to have
White Cutter or Council's working together in the best way possible for the collective benefit
of their man their communities which means less burden on rate payers happy our communities
and Council's staff and more effective councils so as we've set out in our statement of intent
the organization really exists to do three things first of all to create effectiveness and
efficiency gains for shareholders such as you second lead to help increase the influence of the region
and third lead to help shareholders provide a better customer experience
what less does is provide an opportunity to think regionally without boundaries and to then help
councils use that thing locally to improve the well-being of the community so thinking regionally
means that rather than individual councils trying to solve their problems individually
less can help them work them out with the cost of that spread while still allowing local
choices to whether to implement solutions locally. I think that it's fair to say my observation
would be that over the years of its existence the organization's done a good job but I think
one of the reasons that I've been high is that there was an opportunity seen to be able to
really grasp the company's potential so when I was high the board said that it wanted to undertake
a number of transformative projects at pace and for that reason we are going to end our driving
the organization harder and faster and earlier this year the board committed to do just that.
We are looking to be bolder, more disruptive to enable you to help you transform
how you and other Wacca tool councils operate. We also want the afraid of failing and by that I mean
recognising the opportunities worth pursuing as long as we do it fast. Coming from the
private sector having spent 35 years in the private sector my observation would be that
there's nothing wrong with failure as long as you fail fast and fail cheap.
So with that in mind and looking ahead over the next 18 months there are really three core
elements to what we're doing. There are some key strategic projects which we'll be looking to
advance as fast as possible and you'll see those projects in the statement of a team.
There are some businesses' usual projects and in addition I've asked for a re-examination of
some of the work that we're doing to see whether we should stop doing it.
As you'll appreciate it it's really fundamental to perceptions of success of an organization
that they seem to be making progress month by month. So one of the things we've done is introduced
a lot more careful tracking about what it is that we're doing and whether we're being successful
and we're looking to improve the communications to key council staff as well.
I've set to my board colleagues and you'll be aware on sure that everyone sits around the
last board with the exception of me as a chief executive of one of the member councils.
I've set to my board colleagues that they are really the difference between last succeeding and failing
and the reason for that is that they are the ones who will dictate the
resourcing and prioritisation and cooperation which is a quarter to less projects.
And I'll be the point pretty clearly that without their total commitment the organization will fail,
but equally their success, lesser success will be their success and vice versa.
So turning now to what means for your council.
Think three things. First of all you should consider this organization as an extension of your
vision of building the future together to promote the well-being of wipe our district and its people.
We've both got a role to play in providing solutions to the high growth region of the wipe
hotel. We both recognise the need to do more with less to drive cost out of local councils.
We both want to ensure that nationally the wipe hotel region punches of
babbits wait by showing that the region can provide joint up services across the region.
And we both want to improve the well-bealing of the community. Indeed it's in your vision.
Secondly as an organization as I've said before we're not limited by boundaries we're tasked with
thinking regionally to enable you to act better locally. And I think the opportunities to work with
you and your companion councils to achieve your aspirations are boundless,
regardless and possibly even more bit close off COVID-19. Thirdly obviously by necessity we need
resource to achieve our outcomes and you'll see that some of the initiatives that we've proposed
in the statement of intent will require some upfront investment in order to achieve some
mid-to-long-term savings. Now I said I would finish with a few words on coronavirus.
It won't surprise you to know that as a board we've discussed very early on whether we should
make any substantive changes to our work program to reflect what will be a new reality.
What we concluded indeed was that in fact we should keep doing what we're doing because it's
going to be even more important. Moreover it's going to help rebuild the region and increase resilience
our view is that in a post COVID-19 period during the recovery period there'll be need in the
region for at least the following three things. First security of public works to enable a
private sector to plan long range and I think importantly commit to training and for this staff
to commit the stay in the region. Secondly a demonstration of restraint by public bodies on
what might be perceived as non-essential spending in other words doing more with less.
And thirdly motivation and encouragement and development of current counselor staff.
Now we're planning to deliver all of those already through our work program has set out on the
statement of intent. So thank you for the opportunity to talk to you. I obviously wish that I could
have spoken with you in person but now doubt that opportunity will arise sometime shortly in the future.
Calvin and I are more than happy to take any questions Mr Chair but I wondered Calvin if there
is any additional points that you want to make? Well, Calvin Peter, thank you.
Okay thanks very much for that. As you mentioned the last has been active in our
20 accounts for a number of years now and been very successful, particularly with Rata, the
roading accord but what's happening now is an absolute step change and I totally agree with what
you said about it being more important post-COVID rather than less. So yeah, I wish we have a success
of course. Now questions I think clear yes. Yeah thanks Andrew and I'd great to
our next new advisor and it's with C2 Calvin. I did see through some questions that I'm two
ones that I'd just like to ask in this forum. The first one is that you've made a strong case for
continuing how you're going at the moment. You know that all those things that you're focusing on
will be more important than ever when we're dealing in the post-COVID era, I guess.
But a lot of the things that are done that rely on the B, I suppose the goodwill account some
of the ideas and releasing resources from their business to work on less stuff and I can
foresee that Councils are actually going to be pretty hard pressed with their own
own staffing resources dealing with extra things that have come out of the woodwork to do with
COVID-19 and so what assurance can you give us that you won't sort of find yourself
behind that you can't get that sort of resource that you do need from the individual
Councils that have normally been really supportive because you know you're so I can just
completely committed to this other work. Calvin would you mind if I answer that question first
and then, John, maybe there's a few additional points you want to make. I think Councilor,
thank you that's a great question. The good news is we had I'm happy to say thought of that as well
and one of the earliest things that we did well before lockdown was when we could see this thing coming.
It was to reach out to Councils to listen to think about whether in the context of any redeployment
of assets and people that they were doing, whether there were going to be some people that might
in fact be freed up to be able to work on some of our projects to make them go faster.
And I was pleasantly surprised particularly from some of the smaller councils to be honest,
about the positive response that we got in terms of offering up staff. That's a first point.
The second point is that more specifically, Calvin's been in touch with the chief executives
of all of the councils I think is recently as yesterday, Calvin, where we've set out some
specific skill sets that we're looking for in order to be able to advance some of our strategic projects.
So, as I say, a great question surprisingly repositive response from the councils that we've
reached out to, but you're absolutely right. The resourcing issue may even flow over time and
it's something we're acutely conscious of. Calvin, did you have any points to add?
I think that sort of covers the rule of paper to be honest.
Well, that's really encouraging actually. It's good to get that clarification that's great.
Now the question I had was about the energy and carbon management that's mentioned in the
East Side here. I wasn't sure whether that is the carbon order that our councilors sort of
before the last election. There was one of the directions that we gave staff that we wanted
to get something organized and that which would help us. I suppose formulated a plan, you know,
for climate change in that. And this is the energy management that's mentioned that that
may have started. Is that feeding into that order or not?
The short answer is Councillor that knows. Well, it's certainly not the order that you all
refer into. I don't see any particular reason why the people that we use to that we engage to provide
that support to councils could not help with that order if that was something that the
white part executive team were interested in doing. But I'm not actually
probably to the particular, the status of the particular piece of work that you're referring to.
I know that Martin Lynch, who's one of the guys that tends to work with white part
district council, has been doing some the spike work in this area, but I'm not sure whether it's
specifically relates to that report that you're referring to. Okay, I'll well, thanks thanks for the clarification.
Okay, any more questions? No, okay, well, I take you very much for that presentation. And
yeah, particularly now in a period of significant change, that's really great to see the
positivity. We have gone forward even with the weird will we have around a certain moment. So,
yeah, thanks Peter Kelvin very much. Thank you very much, Mr. Chair. Yes. And I see Andrew Michael is
available and we'll talk to us about the LGFA. Thank you for the opportunity. I'll just maybe make
a few brief comments and then touch on the current environment and then leave some time for
full questions. So, LGFA started in 2012 that currently has 60, 7 member councils,
were the number of others in the process of joining. And the current environment has probably just
even for the councils that don't have any depth. They realise that having access to finances
importance, that's probably speeding up there. They're time table for joining. LGFA
is based on similar models in the Scandinavian countries, the longest of those, there's an
dimat that's been going for 130 years now. So, what LGFA wants is to be a very long term provider
of financing to the local authority sector. The objectives are interest savings on councils
debt to provide a range of borrowing options. So, short term and longer term financing. And probably
the most important one is access to debt markets. And that's been the area that's picked
in the most challenging going over the past couple of months.
In terms of the financials, the profit for the year to join 2020, which was forecast to be 10 million
is on tracks, or even ran the part numbers for April yesterday. And again, the monthly profit
is on track. A lot of the forecasting that's in the draft, SOS, just our data, it's just been
super seeded by the events that we've seen the last few months. But that said, just remember that
LGFA has $10 billion of lending to the sector. So, we borrow from investors and on lending
that nearly time we do, we take a small margin. So, the profit really on all that lending is locked
and until those loans mature. So, even though the may will be some variability in profit,
a lot of it is locked in. That said, the profitability probably shouldn't be your primary concern
that as we're councils get the savings, as the savings on the interest costs and suitment
to your own accessing of finance. So, that's probably the key then. The current environment
interest rates are low, so maybe that's one little bit of good use for councils. So,
short-term interest rates, councils like yourself can borrow below 1% now.
Long-term, we just completed a $1 billion data show just over a week ago. So, we borrowed for
six years and we borrowed at 1.46% for a billion dollars. So, we will add on 20 points to councils
or 25 points to wipe our competitors. So, you'd be accessing long-term money, six year money
at around 1.7% just to give you some idea of a borrowing cost. So, that's one but a good news.
Probably two or three weeks ago, we were receiving recall borrowing requests from councils.
There's a lot of councils knowing that maybe, you know, fee income is dropping and they needed to
get more money into to cover that. So, we've never had a month. We've had a higher amount of borrowing
costs. LGFA was the first non-government entity. Well, entity other than the government to issue
in New Zealand since the level four lockdown was imposed. For a while, investors were very reluctant
to invest. It's just, you know, they're worried, even if we buy it, we won't be able to sell things
in the such that whole risk of version. That we had two developments. One was LGFA have a $1 billion
standby facility from the New Zealand government that expires next year. But the minister of
revite finance provider the letter to LGFA saying that the government would roll that over
for a few of the period of time. So, that support from the government was just a, it's really
symbolic to investors that there's going to be that ongoing support from the government for LGFA.
The second thing that occurred is the Reserve Bank announced that they were going to buy back
government bonds are subsequent to that. They added LGFA to be listed securities that they're
able to buy. So, they signal that by back up to $3 billion of LGFA bonds from investors. And
it was that that really gave the confidence to investors that if we buy them, there's actually
going to be another huge buyer in the market for that. So, again, you know, the level of support that
we're getting from the government has been extremely important. There's going to be
significant challenges for councils, particularly in the 2021 sort of financial year.
Part of the working group that DIA running, looking at doing a lot of modeling on council financial
performance. This, well, for the remainder of this year and next year and that's feeding them to
a lot of the other government sort of workstream, such as the recovery sort of workstream. So,
there's some quite sobering reading come out of there. For WIPA, you're probably well-positioned
in terms of your debt levels, not high relative to some of the other higher growth councils in
New Zealand. So, yeah, there are a lot of challenges and that's probably one of the challenges
for us is that potentially we're going to get breaches of the financial covenants in the next financial
year, not the financial year. So, today we've never had a breach of the any of the financial
covenants, but you know, if revenue falls significantly for councils where a large amount of debt
to start with, then they could well breach that net debt to revenue covenants. So, that's something
we'll have to deal with. But for those growth councils, you know, one of the last tools that
really got us, you know, having to cut their capex and again, that's not particularly conducive
to starting growth and the economy and us, we can get the Lorda bit about what the government wants
to achieve. So, I'd just like to, you know, we appreciate that there's no compulsion for councils
to use LGFA. You're still free to borrow from any other sources that you want. So, I'd just
like to acknowledge our cannabis team because Waipa was one of the yearly supporters of LGFA.
We very much value your support of us and, you know, the professional relationship that we have.
Thanks, Andrew. I think, yeah, almost goes without saying, but I'll say it anybody
LGFA is going to another great contributor to the local government, seen genuinely and certainly,
well, I guess Waipa hasn't used your services that greatly, we certainly intend to in the future,
possibly even more with COVID, possibly not, we don't know yet, do we can?
Yeah, it's true, we don't know about, but very comforted by the item, by that 1.7% number,
Andrew, it's on, yeah, that is very well priced and borrowing ability.
I like the one that was below 1% even better, but short to possibly isn't us, that much.
Now, where I think, Andrew, does anyone else have any questions?
Bruce, and then clear. You're still muted, Bruce.
Press the space bar.
All right, I need to keep pressing it, mate.
Oh, okay, I'm learning. 5 change machines, one doesn't work, so one's in the bin soon.
Andrew just owns plain study's free share in cabinol. One has, Waipa has got 200,000 shares at
quite 4% just a simple one. Malewa District have got double hours, but at 9.9, over percent.
Would you explain that?
Yes, the share holding is just something sort of historical. So, when LJFA was started, it needed
25 million of equity. So, there was, I think, 9 or 10 councils that were the initial subscribers,
and then they, onsold, some of the issues to a second group of councils that came in is shareholders.
So, LJFA pay a small dividend to councils on their shareholder.
That is 2% over a cost of funds, but our cost of funds might only be like 1.5% at the moment.
So, on a hundred thousand dollars a share is your only going to be getting like the
three or four thousand dollar dividend. So, that is really not material. So, the level of equity
you have is really not that important. It is the savings that you get on your borrowing costs
that are going to be the big drivers of why councils should be members of LJFA.
So, it really doesn't give you a lot of advantage over a council bit as a non-shareholder,
because again, that is still getting the same borrowing benefits that you are.
It is just simply a fact we needed some councils to put in some equity to get the thing off
off the ground. So, again, you know, grateful for the councils that did that.
I think it is just a double-ing of figure and being an ordinary terms and thinking,
well, how did you get to that, so I know, thank you.
I just I just worked at the App for your Bruce. It's a rounding thing. It's actually
got 0.444 of a perceived and when you double-ed you get 0.88. So, it's just rounding up and down.
Thank you Mr. Chair. So, an honour to all. Clear.
Yeah, thanks. I wish I had as about LJFA saying one of the principles is that
they'll demonstrate social and environmental responsibility. And one question that I've been asking
in past is, will LJFA consider introducing something like green financing or environmental bonds,
you know, like the productivity commission did reports to a low-emissions economy,
you know, a couple of years ago. The highlighted that actually is a bit of a gap.
And New Zealand with this kind of financing where councils could borrow for a project that would be,
you know, reducing emissions or for environmental outcomes. And usually it's sort of a slight margin
lease or something just to say it's a good thing to be doing and we want to encourage councils.
Do you think LJFA would do that or are you talking to government about that?
I think you for that question. It is the whole environmental
issues have been pushed a little bit to the back at the moment because we're getting that's going on.
But LJFA is done a significant amount of work on that and we are intending to offer green
financing to councils. So remembering that it's not LJFA that is doing things with the money.
We're just on leaning us, we're sort of middle. We've actually got all the documents up and
ready to go. But the issue is we're going to need councils to identify green projects.
And then also the street care Greece with this green social and sustainable. So for example, a lot
of the water things actually come under sustainable. So there's a whole industry around that and
it involves identifying things and also there's a certification process of done that. So
a couple of weeks after a day on this topic because if you see the documents, they
must be like a hundred pages long and we've got all that really to go. So it is all happening,
but it will be, it's not going to be compulsory or be up to each council is to tell they use that.
But green investing is a big thing globally, probably particularly in Europe, probably less so
in the US. But suddenly it does give you better access to debt markets if you can at the
green framework. I'm thrilled to hear that you're working on an IH to get you should report on that
so that you're actually preparing or you know, working on a proposal because I think a lot of people
would be looking for that and yeah just say, well congratulations are I think it's great that you
you've made years some I suppose. So groundwork progress and we are looking forward to seeing
you know when you can actually make an announcement. Yeah we don't flat we have a council day
year sort of in July and we don't flag that it was something we intend to do. So we would you know
give the update again this year. But it does something that's definitely happening and we're more
than happy to come and speak to you if you want to have you know more and be discussion about
that side of the business. Thank you. Thanks. Any other questions for Andrew?
No, okay there being a case thank you very much for zooming with us and yeah always got
what see you in place one of these days. Yeah no please okay thanks very much.
Cheers. Okay well thanks for that everybody we have a recommendation that runs from A to G
I'm not even going to attempt to read them all out. I'm sure you can. Yeah sorry Andrew probably
the thing we just need to tune our tension too because obviously a key part of that series of
recommendations is the three letters that are in them and the appendices of appendix some
appendix four five and six. So I do just wonder with just before you before you put the
recommendation we've read us just with just seeking any any input into those three letters
because obviously when you do put the recommendation you will be essentially locking in those
the artex for that can you you're very right I did think of that. I read through them and I
I felt they've seen pretty appropriate as they are because particularly with
of course mind back there particularly with the airport we acknowledge that there was going to be
a major revision in there when they're so why but yeah is there anyone does anyone have any
thoughts on a note or good thanks for that Ken but I think we're all good so
um could I have a move please thank you Bruce and the seconder thanks Lou Cheers
all in favour. All right country no it's carried okay moving on to item number nine
and I see notice there Ken did you want to introduce or
note look I'm very heterogeneity this some two to no matter to um to take and through them the
financial report um yeah I guess the only thing I'm of significance in again there is a
health warning there a little bit like I'm like the four monthly report that you saw at the last
council meeting and obviously anything in the item and the forecast column is um yeah as obviously
outdated by the young by the COVID events so yeah so um a huge effort here's um gone on right
across some cross-couts on the last and the last two or three weeks um to um yeah to
refore cast and you should see the results of the refore cast and you should have a
obviously a quite a different um four cast column in the next um financial report you see
but yeah but look we'll see it they see down the happy format of to take us through the report
all right thanks very much thanks Ken good afternoon everyone so at the currently
standing at the end of March the total income is currently at 74% of the forecast
and the operating expenditure is at 72% of the four year forecast we have vested assets of
a living point eight million recognised to date and that's currently 94% of the forecast
discovered assets is 402,000 um development and reserve contributions
of 4.4 million have been received to date and subsidizing grants at 47% of the forecast
um we have capital expenditure today of 71.3 million which is 51% of the forecast
and they have been no major budget changes this month due to refore casting happening now
there was one arbitrage arrangement made on the 12th March that utilize six million dollars
of short-term tax borrowings and it was on match terms mature and and June and we'll
yield approximately 13,000 of net interest um the rates we have the 62.1 million that's been
set for the year um prior years outstanding at this time of the 62,000 and we have currently
464,000 outstanding at the year to date and then I'll take the rest of the report as
being read and a few months got any questions. Okay any questions? Not a big change really to the
what we have presented the count of meeting so um yeah we've heard about thanks for that NADA
that's great and there being no questions or last for a move for the recommendation
thank you Roger and a seconder. Thanks Claire thanks Claire catch you next time Philip
all in favour. Hi, I country no, that's carried thank you very much and thanks NADA and
move on to item 10 health and safety team or yeah look I thank him issues yes,
Steve has still there so around yeah this is a absolutely um Steve Shaw's baby and um
and a big beaver's beaver's well who has joined us so yeah we end up to Steve and Beaver.
Great welcome Steve and Beaver. Hi guys. Nothing another good new story we need some of them.
Steve wants to start off.
Yeah yeah. Oh mine. Okay so I take a that you guys have read the report
and the attachments to this I do see that there are a couple of questions from
Claire but is there anything else that you guys would like to ask before I get to those questions from Claire
and look slide the floor is yours Claire you had a couple of questions.
Yeah well I mean the first one was that they were for the council entrance
ways with the location of a number of accidents so if you looked into those entrance ways
as they're something to do with that entrance ways like yeah beaver you want to try and
like do you work or do you think what they were just the toe um traps and an entrance ways
and we did get property to have a look and there wasn't anything of significance that we found
can you guys hear me now? Yeah yeah so we didn't find anything of significance
of why they trip the only thing we it was sort of at the lip with the doors
kind of closed and this is at Cambridge so I did probably did have a look at those but we
could find anything that would have caused those trips and we haven't had any
reported sense so it may have been just one of those things but we are continuing to monitor
anyway. Yeah yeah I mean we'll just be our luck that you know
our facilities are causing a problem for people that are coming into this
yeah yeah so I just thought bigger to now a bit more about that yeah okay can you hear me?
Yes yes yes wonderful I'm so sorry I lost my voice there for a minute
so I clear I understood you had another question as well and that was regarding
what ways we have to keep track of how how to say do resources and processes have been utilized
yeah that's a really good question perhaps if you go to the the A3 or the big
report on a page above the Health and Safety due diligence plan monitoring above that as the
Health and Safety lead indicators now these lead indicators are basically the resources
and the contractors that we use and so essentially what we pay for and that's how we monitor
and provide to you the details and what we're spending our Health and Safety budget on.
We do have a very small Health and Safety budget obviously but that what does Health and Safety
lead indicators show is that we we pay an ongoing fee to the White Cat Occupational Health
Consultancy who deliver our Health Monitoring Services we also provide money to the EAP service
which is so provides I guess counselling services to all of our staff we also have training
Health and Safety Training so we have set aside 27,000 for Health and Safety Training in an
annual year and that's that obviously is first day of refreshers and Health and Safety Committee
Training as well as any investigation training which we're looking at at the moment and our
regular conflict training which is obviously comes out of that budget as well and these are all
reported through these reporting mechanisms to yourselves and also to the Executive Team
so I guess that's one of our due diligence in how we show that we are utilizing external resources
and finances appropriately. Honour that that's a great explanation and I can see how it all fits together.
I guess I was wondering about how you knew if a distant individual staff members were actually
you know knowledgeable about Health and Safety Practices or if they were starting new task
or something that they they they they they they they they they get the right briefing and the
stuff like that like you confident that that kind of sort of more grassroots those processes
I think be a feel for a jump any but I'm actually very confident because we have some
very good well educated Health and Safety representatives now and I must say they are
committed they they attend the meetings they go back to their respective teams and they
disseminate their information you know we're making sure that any training is out there
I've got beef and tearing out working with all staff and specialty leaders and supervisors
about how to keep their staff safe. I know that's great thank you.
Yes, thank you can you hear me all right I can. No it doesn't seem to be coming through my head for
I think this is a great report but the question I have is is the
anywhere that we can assess some of the external influences on our teams health and safety
from COVID-19. Yes absolutely and again they feel free to jump in here this report only
covers the period from November through the February so critically it misses essentially misses
all the COVID-19 that will come in the next report but yes absolutely we are we have a staff monitor
or staff register which we monitor the health and well being of all our staff
any that have immunocompanized health issues we are aware of where our staff are what they're doing
and with us like we're moving to level three next week we've gone out to all managers
to advise us of we're exactly this staff are going to be working whether they will be continuing
to work from home whether we will have some like our parts operators working back out in the
community and from the health and safety perspective we're working up some really good protocols
around how to keep in the safe so I hope that answered your question council good. Yeah I was more
wondering about whether any of the external influences of which we got not controlled you know
that they're actually finding in their own family circumstances and something like that
that's actually affecting their mental state which obviously is a health and certification.
I can come in here if you like Steph I've just come out of a webinar with EMA in which
one of New Zealand's leading people on Health and Safety Poor Javi was part of so that actually
ruled up quite a few ways on how this can be managed in multiple levels and I know that our
Viper team have been working along those same lines so you know this is all pretty new to
everybody so we're still writing up those protocols and hopefully getting everything in place prior
to actually going out next week on level three. Oh good big great to see those thanks.
Right anybody else? No I just like to say it's it's great to see your Health and Safety
Program maturing each each report that we get and I just want to say I think your one page
Gary's Health and Safety Commitment is a that's a really really good
um you know I think to put in place um there's nothing like everybody in the
organisation seeing that the CE is committed to to the program so uh yeah congratulations on that
thank you for the meeting yeah she is well done okay so um I have a recommendation to
accept the report to ever move the please thank you Claire thank you Elwin
all those in favour please say aye aye country no that's carried thanks ladies that's that's
terrific welcome Phil we're just gonna pass a person motion to move into public excluded
and then go off live I think Roger and the seconder thanks Susan one and favour aye
country no carried so Sam will let you do your thing