Welcome friends to another global capitalism live economic update,
a presentation we make every other month that is sponsored by Democracy at Work
and by the Left Forum. Before jumping into our topic for today, which is a rapidly
changing world economy that we're going to look at in detail. I wanted to explain
and to apologize for a delay. Normally this presentation would have been premiered
on the second Wednesday of the month which would have been May 10th. But two phenomena
intervened that made us postpone until now what would have otherwise happened
earlier this month. Number one and the more important I got COVID. I've never had
COVID before and it really knocked me down for a good 10 days including the 10th of May.
So that had to be postponed because I was literally a too little to make the presentation
plus I had to be sequestered and not in contact with other folks. And the second reason
is a reorganization inside Democracy at Work, the organization that presents these talks
every other month. And so the combination of the COVID illness and the reorganization, both
of which will be behind us by the time we meet again on the second Wednesday of July. So
I do ask your understanding for the exceptional circumstances that made this presentation
three weeks late. Okay, I want to turn then to our topic which is a fast changing world
economy. And let me stress what I am describing is not something distant. The world economy
is no longer something far away if it ever was. It is now an ongoing reality that shapes
everyone's daily life from China to Canada, from Mexico to Paraguay, everywhere in the world
is affected by the world economy because we are now an integrated, economically speaking,
integrated planet. And we have to learn to deal with the world economy because of its immediate
impact on us. It's in that spirit that I want to talk with you today about the big rapid changes
going on in the world economy. First of all, there really are now two major economic blocks
or units that confront each other in a clear dichotomy that was never as clear as it is today.
On the one hand, you might say the old dominant block of the world economy currently called the G7.
Basically that's the United States. It's Western European allies, Canada and Japan.
That's a block. It is very rich. It is very powerful. It has been the dominant economic
reality with a specially dominant role for the United States for many decades.
But there is now another block. And we all have to get used to what that means. The other block
for lack of a similar designation, I'm going to call the BRICS nations. BRICS. And I want to make
clear not only who's in the BRICS, but why and how it is the other block.
First of all, what do the letters stand for? Brazil, Russia, India, China, South Africa,
the BRICS nations. And from everything I can gather, there's at least another dozen countries,
including very large ones, that are applying to join the BRICS. But even before we look at
who else might be joining, there's something remarkable about the BRICS that has to be spoken to right now.
India and China are the two largest countries on this planet by population.
Russia is the largest country on this planet by geography. Any association of countries that have
the two most populous and the one with the largest geography would have to be taken seriously.
The BRICS have been there as a group for some years, most of which they were not taken seriously.
But now, over the last year and a half, they've become much more serious in the eyes of
everyone in the world with the exception of those. And we'll come to that at the end of today's talk,
who have a vested interest in pretending not to see what's going on. Let me dramatize the importance
of the BRICS beyond what I have said. The year 2020 was a crucial marker of something.
In that year, the total GDP gross domestic product of all the G7 nations, the United States and its allies
was about the same as the total output of goods and services, the total GDP of the BRICS.
They were about the same. The BRICS had been rising as a percentage of the world's output
and the G7 had been declining and in the year 2020 the two lines crossed.
Which means that when I tell you what the situation is now, midway through 2023,
the G7 has continued to decline. That is the proportion of the global output of goods and services
accounted for by the G7 nations, United States and its allies, is now below 30%.
Whereas the total GDP of the BRICS nations is today approximately 33%. In other words,
the G7 is no longer the dominant producer of goods and services in the world economy.
It has fallen to second place and falling is what it has been doing for quite a while and gives
every sign of continuing to do so. I am I dramatized that fact by comparing the GDP growth
in the United States in the first quarter of 2023 with a GDP growth in the first quarter of 2023 in
China. In the United States, that rate of growth annualized 1%. In China, 4.5%. You see the direction
of change and this is important because it means that for every country in the world and for most
of the businesses in every country that either are involved in the export of goods and services
or in the import of goods and services, the world economy is changing in the sense that the BRICS
countries are becoming more and more important as sources of capital, as trading partners, relative
to the G7 who are becoming less and less important. And much of today's talk will be elaborating
the implications of this split and changing world economy.
I want to turn next to the military aspects of all of this and I think they are important.
In a way, the long term decline of the economic importance of the G7 nations has had a kind of
parallel, militarily speaking, coming to a crescendo over the last 18 months. But I think the history
of military conflicts after World War II tells us something. Korea, Vietnam, Afghanistan, and Iraq.
Each of those involved a defeat for the United States militarily. It did not achieve
many of the objectives each of those wars that the United States set out at the beginning.
It should have been clear that the danger of using nuclear weapons meant that these would be wars
fought in Asia, land wars, and that the United States would be at a disadvantage even with
the enormous preponderance of economic and political wealth and power that it wielded coming out
of World War II. But one might have overlooked those signs in the wind.
Were it not for what has happened over the last 18 months?
Russia invaded Ukraine and a war commenced in February of 2022 still ongoing that pits Russia
on one side. Ukraine partly on the other side. I say partly because Ukraine is now a totally
dependent economically, politically and militarily on the United States and to some degree, the
NATO partners of the United States. And again, because nuclear weapons are insane and off the
table, at least one hopes. We are left with a land war Russians against Ukrainians supplied by
US and NATO. And so the US and NATO made a decision, a strategic decision to militarily
equip the Ukrainians, but to rely more on an economic war against Russia. And they're in
lay a strategic mistake, which it is clear to most of the world is playing out now. Here's the
mistake. Russia is part of bricks. The bricks is a real alliance of countries who have a determination
that there needs to be a change in the world economy. One that is symbolized and measured by the
decline of G7 relative to the extent of the bricks. Long story short, Russia could shift the
export of oil and gas from Europe. The now enemy over to China and India partners in bricks.
And thereby evade most of what the sanctions applied against Russia were designed to accomplish.
In addition, Russia could turn for all kinds of direct and indirect supports means of evading
sanctions, means of going around sanctions, blunting the political effects of the invasion of Ukraine.
All of this was done in good part because of the power of bricks, because of the number of
countries that seek to join bricks and therefore do not want to alienate one of the key players in
bricks, namely Russia. The whole landscape of economic conflict has changed.
Giving Russia a level of support that made the statements by President Biden and many others
that the economic war against Russia would collapse the rubble, would bring that country to its knees.
None of that has happened. And the repeated escalation of the weapons deliveries to the Ukrainians,
which have not achieved a military victory, have also not done much to change the basic
economic stalemate because that's what it is since the objective of crushing the Russian economy
is nowhere in sight. That's a sign and a measure of the changing world economy.
And here comes another one. As you'll see, I'm able to present to you quite a list.
The next one is called dollar or de-dollarization of the world economy. What do I mean?
After World War II, the global economy was so dominated by the United States that the United
States currency, the US dollar, became the global currency. So for example, central banks around
the world seeking to hold reserves that would give confidence to anybody doing business in the
currency of that country. They would hold and reserve gold, the global value behind money
at the time. And the dollar, which was deemed literally to be as good as gold, as valuable as
gold. So central banks held reserves in gold and held reserves in US dollars.
Something like 80, 90 percent of global central banks reserves were in dollars.
Today, that number is less than half. Under 45 percent of the world's central banks reserves are in US dollars.
Gold, euros, Japanese yen, Chinese you want. They are replacing and then are alone.
They are replacing the US dollar. And the pace of that replacement has accelerated,
most of it happening in this century, that is since the year 2000.
But this is not all. The dollar is less than less used these days compared with 20 years ago,
or 40 years ago, or 60 years ago. The dollar is much less used in international trade.
Goods and services and investments moving from one country to another, often in the past,
were handled with dollars. The world had to hold on to dollars. Businesses had to hold on to
dollars all over the world because their regular business was conducted in dollars.
Soria Arabia took the initiative with the support of the United States in creating the so-called
Petro dollar. An arrangement in which much of the world's trade of oil, a central source of energy,
was conducted in dollars, paid by country A, that needed to import oil to country B, that needed to
export it. And that, of course, meant that you had to keep dollars to buy and handle the energy
requirements of your economy. More and more, literally every week now, announcements are made
where countries, including Soria Arabia, are changing over and trading oil for other currencies.
China's currency, Europe's currencies, even the currencies of Asia, Africa and Latin American
countries. And this has enormous consequences. The simplest one to understand is this.
The United States has been subsidized by the world's use of its currency. One way to see it
is to understand that when foreign countries send goods and services to the United States,
wine from France, software programs from Japan, minerals and so forth from Asia and Africa and
Latin America. And they pay for them with dollars, they're paying with a very cheap piece of green paper.
Cost literally nothing. We get the fruits of labor. We get the creativity of the productive
apparatus of the world for Americans to consume, for American businesses, to use as inputs to their
own production. And all we as a nation have to give in exchange is totally costless pieces of green
paper, the dollar. And then we get a double subsidy. Because of course, as all the dollars go out
to pay for all the goods we import. And those dollars accumulate in the banks, the private banks,
the central banks of other countries, they don't want to hold on to a dollar that pays them
no interest. They need to hold on to access the dollars. They need to be able to get those dollars
because they need them to buy oil and to do the world's business. But they're not earning anything
while they hold the dollars. So know what they do. They turn around and take those dollars and lend them
to the United States government. They buy treasury bills. And thereby they fund the budget
deficits of the United States. They enable the United States government to tax corporations and the
rich, much less than they otherwise would have to. It's a subsidy to corporations and the rich.
As running the deficits always has been. That is the reality of the double benefit that the
dollar as world currency once conveyed on the United States. But the United States is now
losing that subsidy. Losing the ability to borrow the way it once did.
Discovering that it's going to be harder to finance the deficits of the future US government
than it was in the past because the dollars are not out there waiting anxiously to be lent
to the US government as their way of holding the dollar. What will we see in the place of the
dollar? Well basically there's one of two things. Either the Chinese, Yuan because China is the great
other of the United States, the US and its allies that's G7, China and its allies that's the bricks.
But we're going to see a new currency replace the dollar either the Chinese currency or if they can
do it a composite. A new international currency that will be backed by a bunch of countries not just by one.
You know we were used to the British pound during the British Empire being the global currency
and the US dollar being the global currency during the heyday of the American empire.
It will be an interesting question whether the emerging China slash bricks
global dominance economically will make one or a basket of currencies function
as the global exchange medium in the future. Another dimension of the fast-changing world economy
that I want to bring to your attention is the role of China in two basic ways.
China is the emerging economic powerhouse, everyone in the world who pays attention knows that.
And one of the interesting ways in which China is playing this emerging powerful role
is by becoming a global peacemaker. By far the most dramatic evidence of that was the role of the
Chinese in bringing together the bitter enemies Iran and Saudi Arabia who have been bitter enemies
for a long time and efforts to overcome their enmity.
So far as the United States made such efforts were clearly unsuccessful.
The Chinese did it. They have now exchanged ambassadors and the secondary and tertiary
consequences of peace between those two countries are playing themselves out in the headlines every day.
Why is this important? Well the symbolism could not be stronger.
The United States which like to position itself as global head-juman global peacemaker if possible
has now been challenged by another country playing that role in the same tumultuous Middle East
where the United States fancied itself in that role. It now has to share the spotlight
if it doesn't lose the spotlight altogether. But beyond the symbolism of peacemaker,
there's something else going on here. The fact is that over the last 30 to 40 years
we've had relatively speaking peace. Yes we've had wars. The war in Iraq, the war in Afghanistan and so on.
But these wars were well localized, mostly in Asia not only but mostly, but localized. In the general
global perspective, these were decades of peace and the Chinese are a cutely aware
that their rise from a poor third world country with the added burden of being the most
populist country in the world that their incredibly rapid ascendancy to being the great competitive
challenger of the United States took place over 40 years of relative globally speaking peace.
They want the peace because it has worked very well for them. They did not have to disturb
their own economy by going on to a wartime footing. They did not have to debit their own
economy to move militarily around the world. They don't have foreign bases. They didn't create any.
They didn't have foreign adventures. They didn't create any. They could and did devote themselves
to economic development with a kind of focus that has something to do with the extraordinary
performance they have shown us. They have become ironically advocates of an open-world economy
of globalizing continuously. Here's the irony some of you should enjoy.
On the one hand, the term neoliberalism and the term globalization went hand in hand over the
last 30 to 40 years. They were the ideological way of saying how happy Western capitalists were
in the United States in Europe in Japan with the arrival for them of a vast new cheap labor force.
It's a capitalist dream. China was bringing its enormous population and presenting them
to global mega corporations capitalists. Here come to China and in the lesser extent come to
India, come to Brazil and you will have very hard working people who are willing to accept
much lower wages and that will be a profit bonanza for you and it was the last 30 to 40 years
our stock market booms in the Western capitalist area. But while that boom for the West was the driving
force, China was making its own way forward using the neoliberal globalist arguments of an open
economy of having capitalists come to China to produce their what they would ship back to their own
countries. China became the producer for the world. China's manufacturing exploded.
China did better with neoliberalism and globalization than the West who invented those words
and who invented the thrust into that part of the world for reasons of profit maximization.
Marx and Hagle would smile and remind us of the contradictions that beset whatever happens
in the world. Yes neoliberalism and globalization were phases of capitalism growing of capitalism
having its exploitative relation with labor become global. But the ironic contradiction was it
made it possible for China to gain even more out of this capitalist initiative than the capitalist
themselves. So we get the ironies flower. In today's world as the United States and Europe,
begin to comprehend that China made more out of neoliberalism and globalization than they did.
They are abandoning neoliberalism and globalization. Aren't they? They're becoming nationalistic.
Not just Mr Trump with his tariff war against China. Not just the trade wars against China,
but even though Trump is gone for the moment and Biden replaced him, Biden continues and
if anything intensifies a turn away from neoliberalism, a turn away from globalization and the
embrace of a new kind of economic nationalism in which the United States government now followed
by European governments and so on are turning inward. Ego to subsidize their own
industries and enterprises. Less a fair is a vague memory active government intervention is the
name of today's economic politics. That's a reaction to the world economies changing that will
have many, many repercussions in the years to come. Not the least of which will be the
painful discovery by capitalists in Europe and North America that if they really intend to follow through,
one of two things has to happen. Either they will have to pay the wages that are still
relatively high in Western Europe and the United States and therefore be unable to compete very well
with those enterprises that have the advantage of lower cost labor or they will drive down the
wages in Western Europe and North America. But that risks producing a militant labor movement
that can challenge capitalism from within which way that's going to work out either way poses
enormous problems which the current rush away from the olibrolysm and globalization and into
economic nationalism is making people misunderstand. But we're going to have to live through
the new moan that comes, the awakening that what we didn't pay attention to is going to shape
our daily life all around the world. The next aspect of the changing world economy
focuses even more on China. I had mentioned that China in two ways is shaking the world economy.
I've mentioned the one now I want to deal with the other one and the other one has to do with how the
world economy is making sense of what happened in China that enabled them the Chinese to make such
advances during the period of neoliberal globalization. Why did this capitalist strategy? This capitalist
initiative, this capitalist mechanism for profit maximization. Why and how were the Chinese able
to take advantage of that in the way that they did? And the answer is I think to be found
in both the unique successes and the unique failure of the people's Republic of China.
First the success. China broke from the Soviet Union which in many ways was a kind of model for it.
And China also broke away from the United States which in a different manner was also a model for it.
And in the two breaks I think you can find the key to China's growth success.
First of all the break from Russia from Soviet Russia. In the Soviet Union the government moved in
and took over the ownership and operation of Russian industry.
The five-year plans, the council of ministers, the government became the owner operator of
industrial production. Agriculture much less so and only later. But industrial
governmental ownership and operation was a core commitment starting already in the 1920s and
really getting going in the 1930s and since. China did not do that. China did not. China
allocated, accepted, encouraged and financed private capitalism alongside stayed owned and operated
industrial enterprises. That's a break from the model of the Soviet Union. At the same time and
in the same way the Chinese broke from the growth on capitalist model if you like
of the United Kingdom the United States. And in a parallel way it did not focus on prioritized
private industrial enterprises. Enterprises in industry that were owned and operated by
private individuals, individual persons, individual families or individual shareholders via the stock market.
China didn't have an overwhelmingly state owned and operated industry nor an overwhelmingly
private industry. Now what China did was unique and original. It really developed its own hybrid
mixture of private and public enterprises in industry and both of them subordinated to
an effective control from the Chinese Communist Party.
When the Chinese refer to their own system as quote unquote socialism with Chinese
characteristics, it is that hybrid and that supervisory control of a political party, a powerful political
party. That is the unique original strategic form that Chinese economics took.
And it is crucial to how they were able to utilize the neoliberal globalist period of capitalism
to outgrow the very capitalism that put us in a neoliberal globalist phase.
But I said it was also a failure in what sense was a failure.
Well I think the way to understand that is to draw a comparison between Lenin, a key leader of the Soviet
Union, Xi Jinping, the current leader of the people's Republic of China.
You might think of Lenin as having faced the following situation.
Early in the history of the Soviet Union, after all I'm sure you all know that Lenin died of
very few years after the Russian Revolution. So anything he said would have had to be said in the
early period of the Soviet Union. He referred to what they had achieved by their revolution as an
I quote, state capitalism. And he said that the challenge faced in Russia at that time in Soviet
Russia was the capacity or not of the Soviet Communist Party. The challenge it faced was
making the transition from the state capitalism that they had constructed out of the revolution
into a genuine and socialist post-capitalist economy. In other words, could the party
would the party enable the Soviet Union to get beyond state capitalism?
In point of fact, the party and the Soviet society were never able to go that next step.
There are many reasons. My colleague Stephen Resdening and I wrote a book a few years ago trying to explain
why they couldn't make that step. But here I want to confront you and our Chinese brothers and
sisters with a parallel challenge facing Xi Jinping and the Chinese society now.
They have erected a hybrid, a unique original society split between a private capitalism and a
state capitalism. And let me be clear about why I call them capitalism. Why I call all of these
capitalism, whether they're in the United States or in China, whether they're state or private,
because they have one thing all in common. It's that one thing that Karl Marx focuses on
in the capital volume one, the center piece of his adult mature creativity. What makes capitalism
capitalist is that unique relationship between a small group of people who make the decisions,
the employer, the employer class, the capitalist class, the entrepreneur, whatever you want to call them
on the one hand, a minority, a small minority. And on the other, a vast majority, the proletariat,
the working class, the employee class, whatever you want to call them. Enterprises governed by that
dichotomy, a small powerful wealth accumulating governing group and a mass employee
group producing the profits that that minority gathers and disposes of.
Going beyond that, having an economic system in which the enterprise is a community of equals,
one person, one vote, a cooperative enterprise, a workers cooperative, a workers self-directed
enterprise. That was the challenge, Lenin face. And that is the challenge,
Xi Jinping and the others in China also face. And they haven't made the transition.
They never did in the Soviet Union and the question for China is, can you make that
term, will you make that transition? They haven't done so yet. And that may be more than
is reasonable to have expected given that there are society that begins to move in these directions
only after the Civil War is won in 1949. But the question imposes itself by the very history.
And if let's put a different, however this question is answered in and by China,
will shape the whole world economy, whether they accept the challenge and move and make that transition,
or they don't. Either way, the Chinese given their position in the world today
are going to shake everything and everyone. Okay, by way of conclusion, I want to talk
about the rapidly changing world economy in terms of how it is being processed
understood, particularly here in the United States, which I'm in the best position to try to
understand because I live and work here in the United States. And I've had some help recently,
which is so interesting that I want to bring it to your attention. A very well-respected non-partisan
polling institution is called PEW Pew Research Center. And they did a poll here in the United
States of a large number of randomly selected American citizens. The poll was conducted between
March 27th and April 2nd of the year 2023. So it's just a few weeks old. And the Americans
pulled were asked the following question. Please compare this year 2023 with what you believe will
be this situation in 2050 that is 27 years from now the future. In that sense, we want you to look
into the future, look to the year 2050 and answer four questions. I'm going to give you the
question and then give you the percentage answers that the American people gave. Question number one
will the United States economy be weaker or stronger in 2050 compared to what it is today?
66% of Americans said that the U.S. economy will be weaker.
32% said it will be stronger. Two to one, over two to one, saying that they believe the United States
would be weaker. In terms of today's presentation that the decline of the G7 in the view of most
Americans will continue. Second question, will the United States be less important in the world
or more important in the world in 2015 compared to now? 71% said that the United States will be
less important than it is today. 27% said it would be more important.
Third question, the United States will be more politically divided in 2050 or less politically divided.
77% said more politically divided. 21% said less so. And the fourth and final question
the gap between rich and poor in the United States will grow or it will get smaller.
81% of the American people believe the gap between rich and poor will be worse will be larger
in 2050 than it is today. I want to draw a conclusion in conclusion for today.
The American people understand maybe not the facts in the figures, maybe not the particular details,
maybe not the speed or rate at which the changes are happening. But they clearly understand
that the world is changing in ways that diminish externally and internally what the United
States once was and what it is fast becoming less of. And I want to contrast that with the
statements and I believe the beliefs of the leaders of the United States. Not just the Republican
and Democratic Party politician leaders but much of the mass media, much of the academic world,
so they too are engaged in something which really has no nicer name than a massive quantity
of denialism. They don't want to see what is going on or if they see it they pretend it isn't
significant or if they can find some statistic that makes things look better they hype those statistics
in order to avoid confronting the kinds of issues I have tried to present here. In some ways
is even more impressive than the relative decline of the United States and the G7 relative to China
and the breaks. Perhaps even more important in the long historical run will be this gap
in the understanding and the consciousness of the people who have to live the decline versus the
people who make their living pretending and insisting that that decline isn't happening or isn't
going to have mammoth effects. My own conclusion and I leave you with that is that the pace of change
the rise of the bricks, the collapse of the dollar, the rise of China, the outcome so far
of the Ukraine war, these are powerful messages and measures of a fast changing global economy.
A famous leader once said to his associates who were complaining that there wasn't enough change.
He said to them, for decades nothing seems to happen, nothing much changes. Then in a few weeks
decades happen. I'm quite convinced that in the world economy we now live in, we are experiencing
weeks during which decades are happening. Thank you very much for your attention. I hope these
presentations on global capitalism meet with your expectations and in any event. I look forward
to being with you again for the next installment on the second Wednesday evening of the month of July
2023. Thank you.