One small step is a leap towards the future.
It's the pursuit of knowledge and awareness.
Through much needed transformations and greater ideas.
One small step is a leap towards the future.
It's the pursuit of knowledge and awareness.
Through much needed transformations and greater ideas.
We gain wisdom and knowledge.
From kids to adults we become engineers, scientists, lawyers, entrepreneurs, artists, leaders and much more.
For destiny we'll reveal our true potential.
How do I get there?
How do I know my moments?
Where do I belong?
At each corner, every nook in cranny is the light to develop and grow.
It is the freedom to gmail and flutter.
Everything is a trigger towards something bigger.
In the right space, creativity is a river.
Like types hitting sounds, we find our tribe.
They stand by us, regardless of where we come from.
What or how we think.
What we say, what we speak.
At times, the going gets tough.
Yet, we can strengthen to hold on to what we love with all our passion.
We dance.
We sing.
We run.
We ride. We travel to the ends of the world.
We perform. We shine. We go beyond.
We are that one extra stroke of brilliance.
We always go that extra mile. We discover new paths.
We are prepared to step into the unknown.
We go out to inspire.
We take that one small step. We leap.
Stay hungry for life and follow your passion.
To round the world, all it takes is one small step.
We are the world.
Christ University lives ahead in this dynamic global environment.
Our resilience and agility ensures that.
Through our spirited campuses, we make an impact for contribution to the world.
We nurture all person development and they are equipped to face the challenges of life and go beyond.